Peter W. Neurath Papers MS132
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Peter W. Neurath Papers
1950 -- 1977
1944 -- 1977
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Neurath, Peter W.
MS132
1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of articles and manuscripts written by Neurath, but also biographical information, Neurath's undergraduate and Ph.D. theses, teaching notes for classes at General Electric, correspondence, newsletters, Neurath's appointment to Tufts, and articles by other authors.
Biographical / Historical
Peter W. Neurath was born August 19, 1923 in Vienna, Austria. He left Austria at age 15 when the National Socialists occupied Austria. He spent a year in Scotland and England after the Friend's Service Committee arranged transportation out of Austria for a number of orphans. In 1940, he moved to Canada. He received a B.A. in 'Engineering Physics' (1946) and an M.A. in Physics (1947) from the University of Toronto. Thereupon, he became a Westinghouse Fellow at the Carnegie Institute of Technology, Pittsburg, where he received his D.Sc. in Physics in 1950. Neurath then worked as scientist in the Transformer Laboratories and in the Materials Research Department at General Electric. During his time at GE, Neurath served as Adjunct Professor in the Physics Department at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, 1952-1954. In 1962, he left GE and joined AVCO Research and Development Division as Senior Consulting Scientist. He worked at AVCO as a scientist and biophysicist until 1968. During this time, Neurath was also a special student in Biology and Physics at Harvard University.
In addition, Neurath began to do research with Tufts University-New England Medical Center in 1966. He became Assistant Professor in the department of Therapeutic Radiology and Director of the Physics Division in 1969. He was appointed Professor of Therapeutic Radiology at the School of Medicine, Tufts University, in 1972, a position he held until his death in 1977. Neurath was also named Adjunct Professor to the Department of Engineering Design at Tufts University in 1972. During his time at Tufts, Neurath co-founded and participated in the Program in Quantitative Biology in the School of Medicine.
Neurath's research focused primarily on the use of physics in medicine, the interaction of electromagnets and radiation in tissue, computer application to medicine, and pattern recognition. He is particularly noted for his work using computers to measure and classify human blood cells and his work on chromosome analysis and its computerization. His research was supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health, the Health Services and Mental Health Administration, the National Cancer Institute, and the Atomic Energy Commission. Neurath was a member of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Association of Physicists in Medicine, the American Physical Society, the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers, the New York Academy of Sciences, and the Research Society of America.
Neurath had three children, Eric, Christopher, and Paul, with his wife Virginia. Neurath participated in several community organizations in Winchester, Massachusetts, including the Ecumenical Association, the Winchester Council for Community Action, and Neighbors for an Open Winchester. He became a United States Citizen in 1954. He died from a heart attack on July 2, 1977, at the age of 53.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Neurath, Peter W.; Faculty papers
- Professional Papers, 1944 -- 1977; 1950 -- 1977; MS132.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Peter W. Neurath's records from 1945-1977. Included are primarily articles and manuscripts written by Neurath, but also biographical information, Neurath's undergraduate and Ph.D. theses, teaching notes for classes at General Electric, correspondence, newsletters, Neurath's appointment to Tufts, and articles by other authors.
  Arrangement
  This series was originally arranged chronologically; this arrangement has been maintained (rearranging records slightly to maintain chronology).
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Biographical Information, 1964 -- 1977; MS132.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Undergraduate Thesis and Related Article - University of Toronto, 1944 -- 1946; MS132.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Publications and PhD Thesis - Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1950 -- 1951; MS132.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Professional, 1950 -- 1959; MS132.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Technical Information Series, General Electric, 1951 -- 1957; MS132.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Teaching Notes - Modern Magnetism, Transformer Labs, General Electric, 1952 -- 1954; MS132.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Conference on Magnetism, Articles Written by Neurath and Others, General Electric, 1954 -- 1956; MS132.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Teaching Notes - Magnetism, Statistics; Transformer Labs, General Electric, 1954 -- 1957; MS132.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Articles by Neurath and Others, Technical Series, Contributions - General Electric, 1957 -- 1958; MS132.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Articles by Neurath and Others - General Electric, Journal of Applied Physics, 1958 -- 1960; MS132.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Appointment to Tufts Engineering, Phone Lists, CV, 1958 -- 1971; MS132.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Company Papers by Neurath and Others - Avco, 1960 -- 1962; MS132.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Articles by Neurath at Avco, Articles by Others, 1963; MS132.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Article by Neurath: Quick Chromosome Analysis - Letter to the Editor, The Lancet, 1963; MS132.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Articles by Neurath on Magnetism in Living Systems - Avco, 1963; MS132.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Company Papers by Neurath - Avco, Articles by Neurath, 1964; MS132.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Manuscripts by Neurath, Grant Proposals - NEMC, 1965 -- 1966; MS132.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Manuscripts by Neurath and Others, Newsletters - NEMC, 1966 -- 1967; MS132.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Manuscripts by Neurath, Newsletters - NEMC, 1967 -- 1968; MS132.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - International Chromosome Analysis Newsletter (Edited by Neurath), No. 1, 2, 4, 1967 -- 1968; MS132.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Manuscripts by Neurath and Others, 1969; MS132.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - Articles by Neurath - Tufts NEMC, Appointment to Tufts Engineering, 1970 -- 1971; MS132.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Publications by Others, Pack of Photographs and Negatives, 1971 -- 1972; MS132.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - Articles by Neurath and Others, Recommendation for Promotion, Research Proposal - Tufts NEMC, 1972 -- 1974; MS132.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - Articles by Neurath, Newsletters - Tufts NEMC, 1973 -- 1976; MS132.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - Articles by Neurath, Conference Notes, Research Proposal - Tufts NEMC, 1975 -- 1977; MS132.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - Automated Leukocyte Differentiation Research JFB, July 1 1977 [Grant Proposal and Related Material], 1976 -- 1977; MS132.001.001.00027 (Box 1)